Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太と➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
ひびと
栄光の日 生まれの弟･日々人＞
＜日本人初のムーンウォーカーと
なった日々人は➡
月面での事故の影響で
パニック障害となったものの➡
A lunar accident has left Hibito struggling on the sidelines, suffering from a panic disorder.
復帰試験になんとか合格した＞
But he's able to pass a test to return to active duty.
Older brother Mutta continues his long quest to the moon,
＜一方 日々人の遥か後ろから
月を目指し始めた兄･六太は➡
ついに月のミッションの
バックアップクルーに任命され➡
having finally been selected as a
backup member for a lunar mission.
訓練を始める｡しかし
月へ一緒に行くメンバーは➡
And he's about to begin training.
However, his fellow crew members are a unique bunch.
ひとくせも ふたくせもある
連中ばかりだった＞
現在
Hey, Mom...
(クリス)ねえ ママ｡
もうすぐ６歳の誕生日だよ 僕｡
I'm gonna turn six soon.
あ～ そうね｡何か
今 欲しいおもちゃとかあるの？
Yes, you're right.
Is there a particular toy you want?
うん｡おもちゃじゃないんだけど
僕ね…➡
Nope, I don't want any toys.
I really want a globe of the Earth.
地球儀が欲しいんだ！
あとね クリスマスにはね
月のやつも頼むんだ サンタに｡
And on Christmas, I'll ask Santa for a moon globe.
そう…いいわね 地球儀！
Really? I think that's wonderful.
《私はとても嬉しかった…➡
I was very happy...
ただ そのことが
たまらなく嬉しかった》
His words made me very happy.
I can't get lost in what I'm doing, nothing works out
I don't want these endlessly dull days
I hope I can move on
before the call of freedom drags me away
What's your wish?
I just want some real courage
We all stare doubt in the face, every one of us
Isn't the unpredictability of life the fun of it?
Devote your life to that dream you can't express
Let's go, advance against the wind, our road is long
Embrace the pain of it too
Take a big breath now, and yell
Big Bang! Chase it without fear!
I want to dream so badly it amazes me
There's cowardice in the way of your true wish
Rip that hot veil aside
#95 Our Future
現在
Eh? Really?
(ベティ)え？そうなの？
アハハ…➡
宿題は？もう終わったの？➡
What about homework? Are you finished?
If you have any questions, ask Grandma and Grandpa.
わかんないところは
おじいか おばあに聞くのよ｡
そうね もうすぐ帰るから｡
おやすみ クリス｡
Yes, I'll be home soon.
Good night, Chris.
(六太)もうすぐだからさ｡
(カルロ)そんなもの 今さら
珍しくもないだろう｡
It's almost here.
There isn't anything special about this.
(ﾌｨﾘｯﾌﾟ)何回見たって一緒だよ｡
(六太)いやいや 何回見たって
いいもんは いいでしょ｡
Haven't you seen it often enough?
Nah, it'll always be a treat to behold.
南東の空ね｡
It should be to our southeast.
おっ！ほら 来た！
Yep! There it is!
あ～ いいねえ｡
Yeah, that's nice.
《ＩＳＳ…》
The ISS...
(通信:ラベル)ヒューストン
ヒューストン➡
Houston, Houston.
こちらＩＳＳ ラベルだ｡
This is Ravel, on the ISS.
This is Houston CAPCOM.
こちらヒューストン キャプコム｡
今日のタスクは 全て終了したよ｡
We've completed our day's tasks.
了解です｡就寝まで２時間…
ゆっくり宇宙を楽しんでね｡
Roger that.
You have two hours before bedtime.
Why don't you enjoy space?
お疲れさま ラベル船長｡
Good job today, Captain Ravel.
(通信:ラベル)ありがとう ベティ｡
Thanks, Betty.
Begin reentry sequence.
(通信:管制官)大気圏 突入開始！
Temperature of outer hull rising.
(通信:管制官)外壁温度上昇！
Parachutes successfully deployed!
パラシュート 展開成功！
Orion has landed!
オリオン 無事着陸！
Welcome home.
お帰りなさい｡
ああ ただいま｡
Good to be back.
クリスが大きくなって｢宇宙に
行きたい｣なんて言ったら➡
If Chris grows up and says he wants to go to space, I'd be thrilled.
感動ものよね｡
いいねえ
アストロノーツファミリー｡
I like the sound of an astronaut family.
でも たいがい子供は親の希望通り
には育たないっていうからなあ｡
But they say kids usually don't turn out the way you hope.
But this boy has two astronauts' blood flowing through his veins.
(ベティ)だけど 宇宙飛行士２人の
血を継いでるんだから➡
I have a feeling he'll be interested in space.
自然と宇宙には
興味持つんじゃない？
そうなってくれたら嬉しいね｡
I hope that happens...
現在
And so,
つ～わけで…｡
my brother, Hibito, was able to overcome his panic disorder
弟ヒビトは
無事パニック障害を克服し➡
and pass the test to return to active duty.
宇宙飛行士復帰試験を
終えたわけであります｡
(ﾌｨﾘｯﾌﾟ)マジかよ｡
(ｶﾙﾛ)パニック障害だったなんて
そんな話 初耳だな｡
Really?
I had no idea that he suffered from panic disorder.
So, when will Hibito start training again?
(ﾌｨﾘｯﾌﾟ)で ヒビトは
いつ訓練に復帰すんだ？
ん？…そういえば いつだろ？
Oh, good question.
まあ…
そのうち すんじゃねえかな｡
Well, it should be soon.
じゃあ次…次はベティに
話してもらおうか｡
私？
Who's up next?
Let's have Betty talk about herself.
Me?
Mutta's the only one here who doesn't know your history.
まだベティのことで ムッタだけが
知らないことがあるだろ｡
You want me to tell him?
話すの？
ムッタは弟ヒビトについて
話したんだ｡
Mutta discussed his brother, Hibito, with us.
１人息子のことぐらい
話してもいいんじゃないか？
え？１人息子!?
I don't see why you can't tell him about your son.
Eh? Your son?
ベティ 子供いたの!?
(ベティ)そうよ｡
You have a son?
That's right.
I have an adorable son.
私には 可愛い可愛い息子がいる｡
名前はクリス｡今 ８歳｡
His name is Chris.
Right now, he's eight.
へえ クリス…｡
Oh, he's named Chris...
《え？クリス…》
Chris?
After I had Chris, I quit being an astronaut for a while,
出産と育児のために 宇宙飛行士を
退いてた時期があるわ｡➡
so I haven't been to space yet.
だから まだ私
宇宙に行ったことがないの｡➡
旦那も宇宙飛行士だったから➡
My husband was also an astronaut, so Chris grew up loving space.
クリスも宇宙に
興味を示すようになって…それで｡
But...
(クリス)ねえ 宇宙飛行士って
ロケットに乗るの？
Hey, do astronauts get to ride rockets?
フフッ そうよ｡
パパもママも？
That's right.
You both get to ride rockets?
Yes, I'll get to ride one someday.
そう｡ママもいつか乗ると思うわ｡
ねえ 月って走れるの？
体が軽いなら 鳥みたいに飛べる？
So can you run on the moon?
Can you fly like a bird because it's really light?
月だと星は
どんなふうに見えるの？
What do the stars look like from the moon?
パパも まだ行ってないから
わかんないけど➡
I haven't been to the moon yet, so I'm not sure,
but I'll tell you everything when I get back.
帰ってきたら
いろいろ教えてあげるよ｡
(ベティ)あの子…やっぱり宇宙に
興味持ってきたね｡
He's become a big fan of space.
Yeah.
ちゃんと答えてあげないとね｡
ねえ タック｡
You have to answer his question, Tuck.
そうだな｡
I know.
We will now introduce the three crew members of CES-43.
セス
(司会)ＣＥＳ－４３のクルー
３名を紹介致します｡➡
マイケル･エアロフ！➡
Michael Aaron.
タック･ラベル➡
Tuck Ravel.
And the captain, Brian Jay!
そして船長のブライアン･Ｊ！
So is he back yet?
ねえ まだかな？
心配ないわ｡
もうすぐ帰ってくるから｡
Don't worry. He'll be back soon.
[TV](TVｱﾅｳﾝｻｰ)
３名の宇宙飛行士を乗せた
帰還船オリオンは現在➡
The reentry module Orion carrying the three astronauts has just entered the atmosphere.
大気圏に突入中です｡
まもなく交信も回復し➡
Communications will be restored soon and we will be able to see the spacecraft.
また その姿も肉眼でとらえる
ことが できることでしょう｡
オリオン 交信回復します｡
Communications with Orion have been restored.
Cut the alarm!
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)警報アラームを切れ！
会話の邪魔だ！
(ラベル)了解！
We can't talk over that noise!
Roger.
I just checked the monitor!
今 モニターで確認した｡畜生！
パラシュートが絡まってやがる！
Damn it, the parachutes are tangled!
Tuck, keep Mission Control updated.
タック！状況を管制に
報告してくれ｡できるだけ細かく！
Send as much detail as you can.
Michael and I will calculate our current velocity and time remaining before impact.
俺とマイケルは 落下速度と
地上までの時間を計算する｡
R-Roger!
りょ 了解！
今後の事故調査で
きっと役に立つ｡
The data from this accident will be very useful.
地上まで あと２０秒だ｡クソ…
やり残した事が いっぱいだな｡
Twenty seconds until we hit the surface.
Damn, there was so much left I still wanted to do.
買ったまま聴いてない
ＣＤとか➡
I never got to listen to the CD I just bought.
連続ドラマの『ラストワールド』
だって シーズン２の６話目以降➡
And I only watched up to episode 6, season 2, of Last World.
まだ見てない｡
そいつは いいとこで
見終わったな マイケル｡
You chose a good place to stop, Michael.
あのドラマ ６話目以降は
超つまんないぜ！
Huh?
After episode 6,
that show really sucked.
現在
(ベティ)あの事故のあと 私は
もう自分は➡
After the accident,
I never expected to be an astronaut again.
宇宙飛行士に戻ることは
ないだろうって思ってた｡➡
クリスを
不安にさせるだけだと思って｡
I thought it would only make Chris worry.
(ベティ)だけど ３年程してあの子
地球儀が欲しいと➡
But three years after the accident, he asked me for a globe and began to talk about space again.
言い出して また
宇宙の話を はじめたの｡
Hey, Mom... What does Earth look like from the moon?
(ｸﾘｽ)⦅ねえママ 月から見た
地球って どんなかな？⦆
(ﾍﾞﾃｨ)私は それがうれしくて｡
父親の代わりに➡
It made me so happy.
I want to give him an answer...
私が あの子の問いに
答えるつもり｡
in his father's place.
(ﾗﾍﾞﾙ)⦅いいね アストロノｰツ
ファミリー｡➡
I like the sound of an astronaut family.
そうなってくれたら うれしいね⦆
I hope that happens...
(ｱﾝｶﾞｽ)着陸船は 逆噴射で減速して
月に降りるからね➡
The landing module uses reverse thrust to slow its descent.
そりゃもう かなり広範囲に
砂が飛び散るわけだよ｡➡
That sends sand flying everywhere.
だから 基地や重機類から
離れた地帯に➡
So the landing needs to occur far from the base or any equipment.
降りなきゃならないんだよね｡
帰還の際は 上の➡
When returning to Earth, only the top part of the lunar module is launched.
ルナモジュｰルのみ打ち上げてね…
発射台として使い捨てられた➡
The landing stage is used as a launchpad, then left behind on the moon.
着陸ステージは 月に残される｡
つまりね このままだと➡
So, at this rate, the area around the base will become a landing stage graveyard,
月面基地周辺は 着陸ステージの
墓場と化し 我々は徐々に➡
and we'll have to land farther and farther from the base.
着陸ポイントを 基地から遠ざけて
いかなければならなくなる｡
(記者)こ…困りましたね それは｡
Th-That's certainly a problem.
そこでね そうならないようにする
第一歩が我々ＣＥＳ－６２だ｡
So CES-62 is supposed to be the first step to a solution.
(記者)なるほど…
ありがとうございます｡➡
I see. Thank you very much.
では次に
雑誌読者からの質問を｡➡
Next, we have a question from a magazine.
｢あなたの 一番古い
宝物は何ですか？｣｡
What is your oldest treasure?
おっ！おはよう ビンス｡
おはようございます｡
Hey... Morning, Vince.
Good morning.
(ラリー)一番古い宝物ねえ…｡➡
My oldest treasure, huh?
まっ これかな？軍人だった
親父にもらった 腕時計だ｡
I guess it'd be this.
I got this watch from my father, who was in the military.
こいつは古いが 俺と共に
宇宙へも行ったぜ｡
It's an old watch, but it's been to space with me.
(記者)なるほど｡いいですね｡
I see... That's a lovely story.
宇宙飛行士の宝物が
知りたいなら ビンスのがいいぜ｡
If you're interested in astronauts and their treasures,
you should talk to Vince.
(記者)ボールドさんの？
やめて下さい ラリー君｡
Mr. Bold?
Stop it, Larry.
いいじゃねえかよぉ
話してやれよ｡
What's the problem?
｢捨てられなくて困る｣っつってた
例の アレだよ｡
Tell them about that thing you can't throw away.
(記者)それって どんな
宝物なんです？
What kind of treasure is it?
あれは 宝物ではありません｡
It isn't a treasure.
宝物を思い出すための…
ただの道具です｡
It's nothing more than a tool...
to remind me of my treasure.
≪おい そっちはどうだ？≫
≪大丈夫だ 問題ない
安定している≫
Hey, how's your side?
Looks good. Don't see any issues.
It's secure.
(ベティ)私には息子がいる｡
名前はクリス｡➡
I have a son.
His name is Chris.
クリスの父親も宇宙飛行士で
ＣＥＳ－４３の事故で死んだわ｡➡
Chris's father was an astronaut
who died in the CES-43 accident.
当然 私が宇宙飛行士に
戻ることは 反対されたわ｡➡
Naturally,
everyone objected when I said I wanted to return to being an astronaut.
両親にも親戚連中にも｡
誰も許してくれないのに➡
My parents and relatives wouldn't have it.
In the face of everyone's objections, I didn't have the courage to return to NASA.
ナサ
私ひとり ＮＡＳＡに復帰する
勇気はなかった｡➡
でも 息子のクリスだけは
許してくれたわ｡
But my son, Chris, was the sole person to tell me it was okay.
現在
(ｼﾞｮｰｼﾞ)着いたぞ｡降りろ～！
We're here. Get out.
ん…お～！なんだ ありゃ？
What's that?!
あれは…あの時の？
That's what I saw earlier.
(ｼﾞｮｰｼﾞ)いいか お前ら｡こいつは
このデザートラッツでの➡
Listen up, people.
This will be the last stage of your Desert RATS training.
最後の訓練となる｡
正規クルーとの合同だ｡
You'll be working with the main crew.
い…イテッ！
Ow!
なんだ これ？おい やめろ！
What is this?
Stop it!
お…あっ…｡
(ピコ)ウィ…ヘヘッ！➡
どうだ ムッタ？俺の作った
ゴキブリ号のスピードは｡
How do you like the speed on my Cockroach, Mutta?
(ピコ)まさか お前が ビンスの
控えに選ばれるとはな｡➡
I never dreamed that you'd be chosen as Vince's backup.
バトラーも血迷ったか｡
I think Butler's lost it...
お～ ピコ！
おい ゴキブリ号を踏むなよ！
Hey, Pico!
Whoa! Don't step on my Cockroach!
(ﾌｨﾘｯﾌﾟ)あっ ピコだ｡
Oh, it's Pico.
こっちが サブクルー？
So this is the sub crew?
Yeah.
ふぅ～ん…フ フハハハ！
こりゃ また
ずいぶんイカしたメンツだな｡
You've got a fine bunch here...
何かのジョークかと思ったぜ｡
自分たちのこと➡
I almost thought it was some kind of a joke.
Why not call yourself the "Jokers"?
｢ジョーカーズ｣ってチーム名に
したらどうだ？
ヒャハハ！
いいね ジョーカーズ｡
I like the name Jokers!
いやいや ジョーカーって…
ババじゃねえか！
Er, you mean like the playing card, the joker?
フフッ…ババだ｡トランプで
言やぁ お前らババだろ｡
Sure...
You guys are like the jokers in a card deck.
ババが５枚｡で それを
つかまされたのが エディ船長だ｡
Five jokers.
And Captain Eddie's the lucky fella who got dealt this hand.
ピコ 無駄話はもういい｡
はじめてくれ｡
Pico, that's enough chitchat.
Let's begin.
Yeah, yeah.
さて お集まりの皆さん これから
この デカイブツについて➡
Okay, ladies and gents...
I'm going to explain what this huge thing is.
説明しよう｡こいつは 俺が
開発指揮をとった➡
This is a new landing module that I'm in charge of developing.
新型の月着陸船だ｡飛行士が
乗る ルナモジュールと➡
Lunar Module
Landing Stage
It has the lunar module, which carries the astronauts, and the landing stage, which acts as a launchpad.
発射台となる 着陸ステージ｡
(ピコ)その間に もうひとつ｡
車輪付きの脚➡
But in between,
we have a new Altair equipped with STITCH, legs with wheels.
スティッチを組み込んだ
新型アルタイルだ｡➡
アルタイルが着陸した後
スティｯチが６本の脚を伸ばして➡
After Altair lands, it will extend the six STITCH legs and carry the lunar module away from the launchpad.
ルナモジュールごと
着陸ステージを離れる｡➡
ルナモジュｰルはスティッチの脚で
基地まで移動し➡
The lunar module will move, on its legs, to the base, and dock with the air module.
そのままエアロックでドッキング｡
飛行士は 一歩も➡
The astronauts will never have to step outside.
船外に出ずに 基地に
入ることができる｡
(ピコ)そして 帰還時｡
飛行士達の乗った➡
And after the lunar module launches to send the astronauts home,
ルナモジュールを打ち上げた後は
月に残った スティッチの脚で➡
the STITCH legs can be used to move the landing stage.
着陸ステージの移動も可能だ｡
つまり スティッチがあれば➡
Which means that STITCH can be used to gather the landing stages in one area,
着陸ステージを
１箇所に まとめといて➡
毎回 同じ着地ポイントに
着陸できるってことだ｡
so astronauts can always land at the same point.
すげ…｡
便利｡
Super...
Convenient...
(ピコ)さあ それじゃまず
正規クルｰから乗り込んで➡
So let's begin by having the main crew get inside and try the controls.
操縦訓練といこう！
いやいや 終わった終わった～｡
ようやく今日の酒が飲めるな｡
Whew, it's all over...
I finally get to drink.
君は 昼間から飲んでるだろ？
Weren't you drinking earlier today?
ああ｡それにしても まさか
叶う日がくるとはな…｡
Still, I never thought we'd make it happen.
叶う…とは？
Make what happen?
う～ん…リックが宣言した
俺らの将来だ｡
Remember when Rick told our futures?
Rick would become a flight director,
(ピコ)いつか リックが
管制官になり➡
宇宙飛行士になったビンスに
指示を送る｡そのビンスは➡
relaying instructions to you, the astronaut.
And you would be riding in a spaceship I built.
俺の作った宇宙船に乗る｡
それを言ったリックは いない｡
But Rick's no longer here.
ああ｡すべて
叶うわけじゃないが➡
Yeah, we're missing a link.
俺の作った アルタイルを
お前が操縦し 月まで行ったとき➡
But when you fly my Altair to the moon,
管制室から着陸の誘導をするのは
キャプコム担当の宇宙飛行士…｡➡
the astronaut serving as CAPCOM, at Mission Control,
お前の控えを任された
ムッタの指示で 降りるんだ｡
to guide your landing
will be Mutta, your backup...
The starlight illuminates my future, it's wow... truth
It's 3 AM, and I dream awake
With no idea of my future
only impatience consumes me
I have a thorn in my heart that won't allow me to lose to him
I'm walking a path of thorns I made for myself
But I won't forget the love I found
And I won't forget the ones close to me
I realized you cannot live your life alone
The starlight illuminates my future, and we are all shooting stars
My holy wishes turn all our sad lies into something better
Our orbits have gotten separated,
but I'm fine if you are close
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#96 Astronaut and Father
We're also training hard,
＜ムッ君たちとは別の形で
僕や新田君も➡
though under different circumstances than Mu and his fellow crew.
ひたすら訓練を行っていた｡➡
何を目指しているのかも
あいまいなまま＞
And we still don't know what we're training for.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Astronaut and Father"